<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>延喜式ファイル</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>国立歴史民俗博物館メタ資料学研究センター</publisher>
                <idno type="PID">o:depcha.engi_shiki.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p/>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020-03-31">31 March 2020</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>千葉県佐倉市</settlement>
                        <repository>国立歴史民俗博物館</repository>
                        <collection>集英社版延喜式</collection>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author>藤原時平・藤原忠平</author>
                            <title>延喜式</title>
                            <note>
                                <p>ここに史料の説明が入る。</p>
                            </note>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <variantEncoding location="external" method="location-referenced"/>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body><div n="39" type="巻" subtype="式">
            <div type="首題">
                <p>*Engi shiki/*, scroll39 〈Royal Family Register Office・Royal Meal Office〉</p>
            </div>
            <div ana="正親" n="39" subtype="条" type="式">
                <div type="式題"><p>Royal Family Register Office</p>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.1" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="諸王年満"/>
                    <note type="summary">Age of Royal Recipients for Seasonal Clothing</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100101 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100101"
                        xml:id="item39100101">Every year if <seg xml:id="footnote3910010101">a
                            prince or princess</seg> reaches <seg xml:id="footnote3910010102">twelve
                            years old</seg>, the Capital Office should report that information via
                            <seg xml:id="footnote3910010103">a parallel memorandum (*i/*)</seg> to
                        the Ministry of the Royal Household in the twelfth month. Then the Ministry
                        should send the memorandum to the Royal Family Register Office to check the
                        list against their existing roster. After finishing all of these procedures,
                        the Royal Family Register Office should return the memorandum to the
                        Ministry. The prince or princess in question will receive seasonal clothing
                        after the Council of State's order is issued in the following New Year.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910010101">In the Law on
                        Personnel of the Yōrō Code, "prince" (王) and "princess" (女王) refer to the
                        monarch's offspring of two through four generations removed.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910010102">Here, the premodern
                        East Asian way of counting age, in which a person should be one years old at
                        birth and gain another year at the New Year, is used to count to age
                        twelve.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910010103">A parallel memorandum
                        (移) is an official document format that is used to communicate between equal
                        offices in the *ritsuryō/* system.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.2" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="王定"/>
                    <note type="summary">Authorized Number of Princes or Princesses Receiving
                        Seasonal Clothing</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100201 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100201"
                        xml:id="item39100201">The authorized number of <seg
                            xml:id="footnote3910020101">princes or princesses</seg> who can receive
                            <seg xml:id="footnote3910020102">seasonal clothing</seg> is 429. If a
                        vacancy is created due to a death of someone who has been receiving seasonal
                        clothing, the person who is next in line should fill the vacancy. However,
                        if a vacancy is created because someone is given a surname and made a
                        commoner, do not fill that vacancy but promptly reduce the authorized
                        number.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910020101">The original term for
                        "princes and princesses" is *shoō/* (諸王). I interpreted the term in this
                        context to include both genders.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910020102">Seasonal clothing,
                        *jifuku/* (時服), was given twice a year.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.3" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="諸王計帳"/>
                    <note type="summary">Register of Princes or Princesses</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100301 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100301"
                        xml:id="item39100301">Have <seg xml:id="footnote3910030101">the appropriate
                            offices</seg> draw up two sets of a register of <seg
                            xml:id="footnote3910030102">princes and princesses</seg>. The Royal
                        Family Register Office should sign them, and after the Capital Office
                        completes all the procedures, the Royal Family Register Office should keep
                        one of the copies. After receiving <seg xml:id="footnote3910030103">the
                            order of the Ministry of the Royal Household</seg>, which confirms that
                        the princes or princesses have reached the eligibility age for receiving
                        seasonal clothing, the Royal Family Register Office should check the
                        information and report it to the Ministry.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910030101">The appropriate
                        offices refer to The Capital Office and the Royal Family Office.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910030102">This section on the
                        Royal Family Register Office deals with royal offspring of both female and
                        male genders, so it is logical to translate *shoō/* (諸王) here as princes and
                        princesses.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910030103">This *fu/* (符) refers
                        to the order of the Ministry of the Royal Household rather than the order of
                        the Council of State.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.4" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="同世同名"/>
                    <note type="summary">Princes or Princesses of the Same Generation with the Same
                        Names</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100401 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100401"
                        xml:id="item39100401">Regarding royal offspring who hold court posts and
                        receive seasonal remunerations based on their posts: If there is a prince or
                        princess who shares the same name with someone in the same generation,
                        swiftly announce the situation and have his or her name changed. Then record
                        on the register the new names of princes and princesses who receive seasonal
                        remunerations and submit it to <seg xml:id="footnote3910040101">the
                            appropriate ministry</seg>. Ensure, however, to write down the original
                        name below the new name.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910040101">The ministry here is
                        difficult to determine, but it is likely the Ministry of the Royal
                        Household.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.5" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="女王禄"/>
                    <note type="summary">Princesses' Renumerations</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100501 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100501"
                        xml:id="item39100501">On the eighth day of the first month, provide
                        princesses with remunerations. Have <seg xml:id="footnote3910050101">the
                            office in charge</seg> set up seats in the southern courtyard of the
                            <seg xml:id="footnote3910050102">Shishinden</seg>, erect two ceremonial
                        marquees in front of the <seg xml:id="footnote3910050103">Anpukuden</seg>,
                        stack the remunerations for princesses at the south of the marker placed in
                        the southern courtyard, and arrange the facilities inside the Shishinden.
                        When the monarch arrives at the Shishinden, female chamberlains should lead
                        female officials and take their seats. The officials of this Royal Family
                        Register Office should escort the princesses and enter from the Gekka Gate.
                        The princesses should take their seats under the ceremonial marquees first
                        〈the seating order should be determined by their generations removed from
                        the monarch rather than their actual age. 〉 Then, the officials should move
                        to the courtyard and take their seats as well. <seg
                            xml:id="footnote3910050104">The manager of the Royal Family Register
                            Office</seg> should raise the roster, saying "the offspring of Titled
                        Prince such and such." Then princesses concerned should leave the seats
                        under the ceremonial marquees by responding in the affirmative and take
                        their seats in the southern courtyard. When everyone sits, the manager
                        raises the roster and does a roll call. A princess who is called should
                        respond in the affirmative, proceed to receive her remuneration, and then
                        withdraw. The rest should follow suit. The amount of the remuneration given
                        to each princess is 2 rolls of silk and 6 <seg xml:id="footnote3910050105"
                            >*ton/*</seg> of silk wadding 〈The remuneration amounts provided at the
                        Feast of the First Fruits should be the same.〉</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910050101">The office in charge
                        is the Bureau of Housekeeping, *kamonryō/* (掃部寮).</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910050102">The main reception
                        hall in the Residential Palace.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910050103">Physicians'
                        Hall.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910050104">The Royal Family
                        Register Office consists of three management levels―a director, a manager,
                        and two second level managers.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910050105">The original text uses
                        the counter, *ton/* (屯), which under the *ritsuryō/* system equals to 450
                        grams.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.6" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="女王定"/>
                    <note type="summary">Authorized Number of Princesses Receiving
                        Renumerations</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100601 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100601"
                        xml:id="item39100601">The authorized number of princesses who can receive
                        remunerations is 262. A vacancy should be filled accordingly, but as being
                        said in the previous entry, do not fill a vacancy if it is created because
                        someone is given a surname and made a commoner.</p>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.7" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="諸王時服"/>
                    <note type="summary">Seasonal Clothing Provided to Princes and Princesses</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100701 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100701"
                        xml:id="item39100701">The clothing provided for the spring and summer season
                        to a prince or princess of two generations removed should be the following:
                        6 rolls of silk, <seg xml:id="footnote3910070101">12 *ku/*</seg> of silk
                        yard, 18 rolls of hemp cloth, and 30 hoes. In the case of a prince or
                        princess of four or more generations removed, follow the Laws on
                        Remuneration. On the first month of the twentieth day, create a record of
                        those who receive spring-summer clothing that year and send it to the
                        Ministry of the Royal House. Do the same for autumn-winter 〈However, provide
                        silk wadding instead of silk yard; and 5 hoes instead of 2 bars of iron.〉
                        Everybody who is titled to receive seasonal clothing should go to the
                        Ministry of the Treasury to receive it; sending an agent to receive it is
                        not allowed.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910070101">The *ryō/* code defines
                        1 *ku/* (絇) to be 16 "lesser *ryō/*" (小両), so 12 *ku/* should be 192 lesser
                        *ryō/*. 1 lesser *ryō/* is 225 grams, so 12 *ku/* is 43.2 kilograms.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.8" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="女王節禄"/>
                    <note type="summary">Princesses' Renumerations at the Two Seasonal Court
                        Banquets</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100801 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100801"
                        xml:id="item39100801">Submit lists of attendees to the monarch in the
                        morning of the two seasonal court banquets―one on the seventh day of the
                        first month and one at the Great Harvest Rite―in order to provide princesses
                        with remunerations.</p>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.9" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="平野祭"/>
                    <note type="summary">Hirano Rite</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39100901 engishiki_ja.xml#item39100901"
                        xml:id="item39100901">Submit the list of attendees of the Hirano
                        Rite―officials, princes, and princesses―to the Council of State.</p>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.10" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="薬師寺"/>
                    <note type="summary">Golden Light Sutra Lectures at Yakushiji</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39101001 engishiki_ja.xml#item39101001"
                        xml:id="item39101001">The Royal Family Register Office should select twenty
                        to sixteen <seg xml:id="footnote3910100101">princes or princesses</seg> in
                        advance when deciding the attendees of the Lectures on the Golden Light
                        Sutra (*saishōe/*) held at <seg xml:id="footnote3910100102">Yakushiji</seg>
                        each year. These attendees must hold no official post, and their ranks
                        should be sixth or lower. Then on the first day of the third month, the
                        Office should submit the attendee list to the Council of State.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910100101">The original term is
                        *ōshi/* (王氏). Under the *ritsuryō/* system, *ōshi/* refers to royal offspring
                        from the second generation and the fifth generation removed. Royal offspring
                        without a specific clan name were also called *ōshi/*.</note>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910100102">A Buddhist temple
                        built in 680 at the request of Sovereign Tenmu (r. 673-686). In 718, it was
                        relocated to its current location in Nara as the capital was transferred to
                        the Heijō Capital.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.11" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="諸王出家"/>
                    <note type="summary">Princes or Princesses Taking a Tonsure</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39101101 engishiki_ja.xml#item39101101"
                        xml:id="item39101101">If a prince or princess takes a tonsure, stop
                        providing him or her with seasonal clothing. Likewise, if a princess takes a
                        tonsure, stop providing her with remunerations at <seg
                            xml:id="footnote3910110101">the seasonal court banquets</seg>.</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910110101">They refer to the two
                        seasonal court banquets mentioned in the 8th entry.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.12" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="諸王死去"/>
                    <note type="summary">Death of a Prince or Princess</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39101201 engishiki_ja.xml#item39101201"
                        xml:id="item39101201">If a prince or princess of the sixth rank or lower
                        passes away, his or her household should report that to the Royal Register
                        Office. And then the Office should immediately report that to the Ministry
                        of the Royal Household.</p>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.13" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="女王地"/>
                    <note type="summary">The Size and Location of Land Supporting a Princess</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39101301 engishiki_ja.xml#item39101301"
                        xml:id="item39101301">The land supporting each princess should be 1 <seg
                            xml:id="footnote3910130101">*chō/*</seg> 〈It is located in the third
                        block from the center in the northern area of the Left Capital.〉</p>
                    <note type="translatorsNotes" target="footnote3910130101">A unit of area,
                        approximately 1.2 ha.</note>
                </div>
                <div ana="正親" n="39.14" subtype="項" type="条">
                    <head ana="闕官"/>
                    <note type="summary">Use of Unpaid Allowances</note>
                    <p ana="項" corresp="engishiki.xml#item39101401 engishiki_ja.xml#item39101401"
                        xml:id="item39101401">Special allowances to compensate for officials'
                        extremely exhausting work should be used for minor repairment or for
                        miscellaneous purposes at the Royal Family Register Office if there are
                        vacant official posts, or if full-time officials or those serving in
                        rotation are absent from work.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div></body>
    </text>
</TEI>
